JOE: When assessing and planning
for the care of a child or young
person with autism, they and their
parents should be able to express
their views, wishes and feelings.
They should also be a part of
the decision-making process
which should always be made
clear and easy to understand.
The child or young person, and those
that know them best, should be able to
talk about what they have done, what
they are interested in, highlight their
strengths and capabilities and what
outcomes they are seeking in the future.
BETH: When a child or young person
with Autism is transitioning into
Adult services and support, all teams
should work jointly to provide support,
further assessment and services
that make that transition positive.
Positivity is always important to help
the individual make better choices,
try new things or learn new skills.
Diagnosis and management should be
reviewed throughout the transition
process, and there should be clarity
about who is the lead clinician to
ensure continuity of care and maintain
that ‘person centered’ support.
JOE: If the individual is an adult,
families, partners and carers should
also have the opportunity to be involved
in decisions about support and care.
Good communication between healthcare
professionals and people with autism and
their families, partners and carers, is
essential and time should be taken to
build a trusting, supportive, empathic
and non-judgemental relationship.
BETH: This should enable support to
be structured to create an ‘outcome
focused’, co-ordinated plan, that
meets the needs of the individual.
It should be supported by
evidence-based written information
tailored to the person's needs.
It should also be accessible to people
with additional needs, such as physical,
sensory or learning disabilities, and
to people who do not speak or read
English, however if individuals do not
have the mental capacity, the code of
practice that accompanies the Mental
Capacity act should always be followed.
JOE: Remember an important thing to
focus on with a person-centred approach
is not to see the ‘limitations’
someone may have, but to see them
as differences and as something the
individual can overcome with support.
Showing empathy and compassion and being
supportive, can help to gain understanding
of the reactions and behaviours
someone with autism may experience.
BETH: By being non judgemental and
not blaming the person helps us to
understand their needs and appreciate
any improvements to their social
skills and interactions with others.
Treating someone as an individual,
can make them feel more comfortable
and supported, allowing them to
open up and take on new challenges.